部分鼍昂υ樘
但本片改自真事件
科W文以及公共n案
@是P於找rg起源的故事
斯德哥摩
1978年十二月
本尼迪克特・康伯巴奇
一切都要念^f起
It has to be back to the beginning.
那r我要做的？-Γ尼斯
Is that what we're doing? - Yes, Dennis.
在_始之前，我要搞清楚
One thing we have to know before we starts,
你什Nr候JR他的？
when did you meet him?
-什Nr候？ -你是指1963年
- Back then? - In 1963 you're talking about?
你t解他幔
What did you make of him?
-不  -我甚至不知道有@N人
- We didn't. - We didn't meet him.
-他r在英  -我r在新晌鳎美）
- He was in England. - We were in New Jersey.
等
Wait a minute.
我都不知道有他@N人，  我知道N?
We didn't even know he existed. Did we know he existed?
我根本不知道他是l
Yeah, We had no idea who he was,
史蒂芬・霍金，他是l呀？
Stephen Hawking, who is he?
都是十五年前了，U勃
It's fifteen years ago, Bob.
不敢相信呀
Can you believe it?
光似箭啊，是幔
Time flies, ha?
霍金的故事
"宇宙是]有起源的
"There was no beginning of the universe.
不是^去  F在是
Past, present, future.
宇宙一直存在  也永h存在"
The universe has always existed and it always will."
史蒂芬
Stephen?
"恒久不"
"It stays the same."
史蒂芬
Stephen?
@是什N？
What is it?
是什N呀?
好了，等等  我有多Lrg
Ok, wait, how long we've got here?
我可不想t到
I don't want be late.
彭R斯和威d在@得1978年Z物理W，Q他奈撮x^阿珀的任何文。1948年_始，阿珀就_始研究宇宙大爆炸理，Kl表了很多文。不^，在r的技gl件下，他的很多^co法得到C。後硌芯糠较蜣De的。cZ失之交臂，由於不止，的Z的Cl也因此一拖再拖
阿Z・彭R斯IZ算t到幔
Arno Penzias was late for his Noble Prize?
我不@NJ
I don't think so.
F在在拍幔
Are we filming now?
是的
Yes.
我l誓，@是你一生中到的
I swear to you, that this is the most profound thing
最深W的|西
you'll hear in your entire life.
您指的是@嘈s，是接下淼墓适拢
The sound, or the story?
音是故事  烧哂惺颤N^e呢
The sound, or the story? What's the difference?
}W本斯
1963年一月
原砟阍谶@
There you are.
你我碚夷
Your mother sent me to find you.
"...f的⒈惶蕴，由新的眄替
"...new matter which has been created to replace all matter.
@一t墓诺浇褚恢边m用，未硪。
This process has always existed and will continued forever.
什N都不改  一切都未曾改"
Nothing changes. Nothing has ever changed."
"@是我的理  我⒅命名
"It's my theory. I have given it a name.
恒BWf
I've called it: steady state.
晚安"
Goodnight."
晚安  霍伊教授
Goodnight, professor Hoyle.
那就是霍伊？
That's Hoyle?
那就是霍伊
That's Hoyle.
-您好  -你好
- Hello. - Hello?
你是？
Who are you?
我是・王德
I'm Jane Wilde.
-我素未相R，是N？   -是的
- We haven't talked, have we? - No.
我是史蒂芬的朋友
I'm a friend of Stephen's.
我在邂逅於另一派Γ他邀我⒓
We met at another party and he invited me.
@派
To this party.
伊韶  伊韶
Isobel? Isobel!
嘿！
Hello.
最近怎樱
How are you?
挺好的
Fine.
我最近也挺好， 你呢
Good. You?
是挺好的  xx
I'm still fine. Thanks.
抱歉
Sorry.
你  你的...
You're, your-
噢，不，]事  xx
Oh, no, thanks, thank you very much.
真是繁的|西  是不是
There're terrible thing, aren't they?
嗯，  真麻
Yes. Terrible.
xx
Thanks.
史蒂芬
Stephen?
@是派  人家]哼想跳舞呢！
It's a party. People might want to dance.
瓦格{的音吩觞N伴舞啊
Can't dance to Wagner.
-敬史蒂芬  -敬史蒂芬
- To Stephen. - To Stephen.
生日快
Happy birthday.
我出去盒悬N？
Shall we go outside?
什N
What?
它我感到自己很渺小  非常渺小
It makes me feel... small. Very small.
外面的宇宙如九牛  我只如一毛
All that out there, us here.
e心  伽利略e了
Don't worry. Galileo was wrong.
}W本斯才是宇宙的中心
St Albans is absolutely the central of the universe.
伽利略已死了  正好是321年前的今天
Galileo died. 321 years ago today.
在你的生日@天
On your birthday.
他改了我σ磺械目捶
He changed the way we thought about everything,
而人害怕@N改
people are frightened of change.
我爸和我^去常常半夜
My father and I used to come out here
砜催@M天的繁星
in the middle of the night, and looked at the stars,
有次看到了一w星的E落
actually saw a star died once.
然了  那其l生在20f年以前
Of course it happened about two hundred thousand ago
但直到1956年的那晚上@景象才髁诉^
but the news didn't reached and open the night in 56.
光速很快  但速度的大小是有档
Light is fast, but it isn't that fast.
抱歉  我Qf物理了
Sorry. Physics.
他都x我好h呀
They're all so far away.
但他看起聿皇沁@拥
But they don't seem it, I mean,
我感X似乎
it feel like I might
我一伸出手就能|摸到他一樱那你最好快c
stretching and reaching them and might just touch them.
那你最好快c
You better hurry up, with your stretching and reaching,
因樗x我越碓竭h
because it's getting further away.
什N意思？
What?
y河系x我越碓竭h了
The Galaxy is moving away from us
相τ谖，它曾_到r速六百f英里
it goes once about 6 million miles per hour,
但F在成|英里每小r了
but this one's about two hundreds million miles now.
我信上帝
I believe in God.
Σ黄  我就是不由得f出淼  我也不知道槭颤N
Oh, sorry. I just want to say, I don't know why.
]PS
It's all right.
你f你感到渺小
You said you felt small,
上帝你感到不那N渺小幔
does God make you feel less small?
直X]什N不Φ  心理作用
It's nothing wrong with feeling inside, it's feeling matters.
所有最好的猜想都是先直X估，再去C的。
All the best idea were felt and argued about later.
垡蛩固拐f^
Einstein said he could
如果他的猜想是Φ模他的小指就有特殊的感X
feel in his little finger if his idea was right.
有你做伴真好  你喜g瓦格{幔
See you are a good company. And you like Wagner?
H上  不，不太喜g  我X得他...
Actually... no. I don't. I think he's...
他怎N了？
What?
浮A    荒
Pompous, and ridiculous.
那你喜g什N？
Who do you like then?
拉赫曼尼Z夫
Rachmaninov.
怎N了
What?
]什N.
Nothing.
那勃拉姆斯呢  史蒂芬
Brahms? Stephen?
我什N都]f啊
I didn't say anything.
披^士
The Beatles.
l
Who?
算了
Never mind.
Jane?
什N事
Yes.
取我吧[披^士的名曲]
Please please me.
什N
What?
畚野[披^士名曲]
Love me do.
我M去了
We should go in.
-我起不  -e[了
- I can't get up. - Come on!
我起不
I can't!
很有趣是吧！
Very funny!
我起不
I can't get up, Jane!
我叫人湍
I'll go and get help.
喂
Hello Jane!
Hello?
得到幔
Can you hear me?
你怎N了
What's wrong with you?
我起不
I can't get up!
把你的手o我
Well, give me your hands.
疼
Will it hurt?
-f真的？  -疼
-The truth? -Yes.
再蜷起硪恍
A little bit more.
很好  F在e  保持住（要hold住.哈哈）
That's good. Now, hold. Hold still.
可能有c不舒服
That's might be a little bit more uncomfortable.
你多大了  史蒂芬
How old are you, Stephen?
我二十一
I'm 21.
你多大了
How old are you?
我可比你大
I'm older than you.
大多少
How much older?
我三十三了
I'm thirty-three.
要猜真有y度，保B得真好，看不出你有33了（了30肀椋大概英文如此）
that is interesting to guess, bad memory might make it hard to.
你是帜男械模窟..  等等 我猜猜
What did you do? Oh no, wait, let me guess.
呃...做保U推N的 ？是y行的人？
Um... insurance sales man? Or banking maybe?
我...我是宇宙W家
I am a, I'm a cosmologist.
哇，挺害的
Oh, good for you.
_始x博
Just start my PhD,
或者f_始考]念什N系
or rather just start to think about what my Ph.D might be.
@程大概要五分
Now it'll take about five minutes.
有rf聊ce的不相干的事
Sometimes it helps, too,
有c椭的
to talk about something completely different.
D移你的注意力
To take your mind off all this,
然後在@空ge的rg^得更快些
and then your time suspend in space will pass more quickly.
rg和空g不能立存在
Time and space don't exist independently of each other.
真的？
Isn't that so?
宇宙也是
Or the universe.
真的
Really?
宇宙中的物|和能量
Matter and energy in the universe.
展_或]合的r空
Open or stop spacetime.
扭曲的r空
Spacetime is curved.
喂
Hello?
不知道，我，我不知道
No, no, We, we don't know.
有很多z查要做，嗯，  好的  再
Lots of tests. Yes, yes, goodbye.
l的？
Who was it?
派ι夏女孩
The girl from the party.
倪@P於你亡的X光片可以看出
The X-ray of your spine with the dying
]有任何物浩饶愕募顾
shows you don't have anything pressing on your spinal cord.
那是好事
That's good, isn't it?
@只是一排查的^程
It's a process of elimination.
你是一F
You're a team.
我是f二位今晚要共同I取Z
I mean you are both getting the Nobel Prize this evening.
我推]他@工作的
I put him up for the job.
他s不肯我⒓用嬖
And they wouldn't even let me in on the interview.
所以我就在周e晃
So I loitered around.
等U勃和I委T的人一起出
When Bob and the interview committee came out,
互相握手，K且
doing their hand shakes and
f著"感x您的光R  o候佳音"
"Thank you for coming and I will let you know",
我就走上前去
I moved in.
我f"你同意用他了吧，是幔
"You gave him the job, right?
你同意用U勃了吧，是不是？！"
You gave Bob the job, didn't you?"
r夥照娴暮擂
It was this kind of embarrassed pause.
我就直截了地f
So I told them straight,
"我和U勃要倪@l走廊@N走出去
"Bob and I are going to walk down the corridor right here,
走出那扇T
and right out that door, right there.
U勃就是榇硕生的
And if you don't want Bob to have the job
你要是不o他@工作
that he was born to do,
在我穿^那扇T之前就告V我"
then you call up before we go through that door."
那是我人生最L的一段路
Longest walk in my life.
62步
62 paces.
我]有回^
And we never looked back.
他不告V我他\喑龅慕Y果
They won't tell me what they're thinking.
t生不f的
Doctors don't.
他自己]搞明白呢
They don't know themselves yet.
我就是t生  伊韶
I'm a doctor, Isobel,
我知道t生的t
I know what they are like.
你是Р＜  老爸
You're a tropical disease expert, dad.
我t解t生
I know doctors.
怎N了  伊韶
What? Isobel?
]怎N
Nothing.
我o你安排为病房
I will arrange for you to have a private room.
不 . 我要像其他人一哟在@
No. I will stay in the ward like everyone else.
你向牛津或蛱岢錾暾了
So have you applied for Oxford or Cambridge?
他不要我，  我在考]威斯菲德
They don't want me, I was thinking of Westfield.
是一所老牌女校
It's an old lady's college.
它的模，呃.我希望它是@拥模有，有，它很...
On the model. I suppose, and, and, It's quite...
字  我字玩造句吧？
Scrabble. Let's play scrabble.
白血病
Leukemia.
他才十二q
He's twelve.
美O了
It was beautiful.
我一出林子，它就立在我面前
I came out of the woods and there was,
一件完美的O
a perfect piece of equipment.
它的天
The antenna.
有像留C喇叭一拥拇罄叭立在上
A great big horn like a gramaphone horn lying on the side.
有一座房子那N大
The size of a house.
就在~s市外20英里的一座山
In the middle of a field, on a hill,
的一K平地中g
20 miles out New York City,
下@些高l噪音（hiss有嘶嘶的意思）
picking up the hiss.
指向星空
Pointing at the stars.
然後高l噪音
And picking up the hiss.
我第一次看@大喇叭的r候  你猜怎N
And then the first time I saw the horn, you know what?
它就难e面w出砹
They flew right out of her.
l
Who?
子
The pigeons.
那（直剑┒十英尺的大喇叭e住了一群子
The twenty-foot horn, has a couple of pigeons living inside it.
-子C  -一大群！
- Pigeons? - Pigeons!
@（直剑┒十英尺的大喇叭是做什N的
What is it for the twenty-foot horn?
除了o子巢之外
Apart from pigeon nesting.
我想y量噪音
We wanted to measure the noise,
碜糟y河系外的噪音
from the outer of the range of the Milky Way.
阿Z建了冷B荷d
Arno built a cold load.
那是什N
What's that?
5英制加龅囊B氮
5 imperial gallons of the liquid helium.
你知道那是多少氮
You know how much helium that is?
那可真是不少呢
That's a hell of quantity helium.
o了你一十分精准的⒄瘴
Gives you unbelievable accurate reference
@幽憔湍芎饬磕闶盏降脑胍袅
against which you can measure the noise you receive.
阿Z做事很精_  他做@|西是最好的
Arno was very precise. He make these things better than anyone.
大概是因槲沂堑乱岬陌
Maybe it's the German in me.
你是德人
You're German?
做了五六年的德人  脾庖蚕竦人
First six years in my life and a big chunk of my temper.
U勃做了很棒的交Q器
Bob made a great switch.
相B的接收器
Two connected receiver
一B天  一B冷B荷d⒄瘴
alternatively to the antenna and cold load reference.
你是在德出生的
Were you born in Germany?
哪年生的  二十世o40年代
When? The 1940s?
不  是30年代
No. 1930s.
噪音就是崃  崃吭礁  噪音度越
Noise is heat. The higher the heat, the more intense the noise.
你或S想t解我接受到的噪音是怎.
You may want to ask that we get noise.
我接收到很多噪音  那意味著有很多崃
We got a lot noise, which means a lot of heat.
不在y河系放出的崃抗之
Far more than the Milky Way should have given us.
打那以後  @就成了我的工作
That was our work, from then on in.
日鸵蝗盏刈聊崃康碓
Day after day. What's all this heat,
@些s（嘶嘶）到底是什N
what the hell is this hiss.
昨晚死了  苦命的娃
Died in the night, poor lad.
我到底得了什N病
What's happened to me?
一般碚f我在家倜媲昂突颊哒
Usually I would sit down with the patient and his family.
求你
Please!
\由窠元病
Motor neuron disease.
什N？具wR床表F是什N？
What, what it is? What happens?
\由窠元是大X中l出\有盘的神元
Motor neurons in the brain, which signal movement,
-他正在衰亡    -那怎樱
-they're dying.     -So?
\由窠元病Qmnd是以p害脊髓前角,
蜓幽XB神\雍撕湾Fw束橹鞯囊唤M
慢性M行性性疾病。R床以上或(和)下
\由窠元p害引起的c橹饕表F,
其中以上、下\由窠元合闶p者樽畛Ｒ。
大X不能向肌肉l出\拥闹噶
The brain stops telling muscles to move,
o法鬟f
the signal's not sent,
肌肉得不到  就逐u萎s了
the muscles are not used, so they waste away, slowly.
要多久呢？
How slowly?
肌肉功能衰退е滤不再有\拥哪芰α
The muscle's wastage causes immobility.
要多久
How slowly?
@逐uc
It's gradual paralysis.
然後呢？然後怎N了？
And then? Then what?
用砗粑的肌肉（平滑肌）c其他肌肉不同，是不受大X控制的
The respiratory muscles unlike most of the other muscles，work automatically.
平滑肌能蜷Lrg拉o和S持力。@N肌肉
不S意志收s，意味著神系y自涌刂扑
，而o需人去考]
-你是指呼吸  -
- Breathing. - Yes.
所以呼吸肌萎s得更慢
They don't waste away so quickly.
但也萎s，最K都萎s
But, but they do, they do, waste away.
是的
Yes.
所以呢？  我⒑粑不常
So what? I won't be able to breath properly，
最K我窒息
And then I won't be able to breath at all.
就像  就像溺水
So it's like, like drowning.
那我的大X呢？它怎樱
What about the brain? The brain itself?
安然o恙
Untouched.
大X不受影
Brain is left untouched.
年pλ碚f @是件好事
He is young. That will work in his favor.
弗m克
Frank?
得他八q的r候幔
Remember when he was about 8 years old,
我在花@e玩天文望hR
and we were in the garden with telescope.
史蒂芬我
And Stephen said to me:
"星星是哪淼"
"Where do stars come from?"
我不知道@原由
I didn't know the answer.
你叫他上床的r候
And you called him into bed and
他仍然@念念不忘
he wanted to know the answer to his question very badly.
那r我就f“e心，我替你去的”
And I said: "Not to worry, I'll find out for you."
但我食言了
I never did.
你牟皇多愁善感的男人
You've never been a sentimental man, Frank.
嗯
No.
你F在要是得善感我怕是消受不起
I don't think we can afford for you to start now.
我去查^了
I looked it up.
@\由窠元病患者越是年p
The younger while you get motor neurone disease,
肌肉萎s的速度就越快
the quicker, the deterioration.
年p於他是件氖.  伊韶
Being young, is a bad thing, Isobel.
最多活赡
Two years, probably no more.
那r我就要扶著他.
Then we must support him.
是的
Yes.
你要退  猿窒氯
You do it, by carrying on.
你要退，他^m生活下去
You do it, by living and carrying on.
他浠  回w他的生活
He's going back to Cambridge, to his life.
你知道霍伊f什N
Do you know what Holye says?
什N？
What?
如果你_一直做直\
You could drive the car straight upwards.
半小r就能到太空了
You'd reach the space in half an hour.
@著y河系_一圈要多久？
How long to drive around the Milky Way?
算y河系的直
You must apply the diameter of the galaxy
用光年做挝
by the distance of one light year.
小菜一碟
Easy.
算
The calculation.
@v  才挠《扰芰砘  得
The car, just had been to India and back, you remember?
x博要多久？
How long dose it take to complete the PhD?
@c研究n}有P
It depends on the subject.
如果一路L呢？
With a fair wind?
如果一路L切且天Y慧，赡辍
With a fair wind and a good brain, two years.
你的博是l？
What's the name of your supervisor?
夏R  尼斯・夏R
Sciama. Dennis Sciama.
5.08697306×10?10英里殂y河系周L
50,869,730.6 million miles, around the Milky Way.
我耐饨缃邮盏降崃
The heat we were receiving from out there
本比⒄瘴锏啥
should be 2 degrees colder than the cold load, the reference.
但它事上要高三度
But it was hotter, three degrees hotter.
比y河系所能a生的崃扛多
Hotter than the Milky Way could produce.
也比其他星系所放的更
Hotter than some of all the galaxies beyond.
所以我猜...
So we felt...
@源^肯定x地球很近
It has to be something close to the home.
於是我提出了猜想，  是是你想出淼模
We had an idea. Or was it you had an idea?
我不得了
I don't remember.
我林林列了一清蔚牟孪
Oh we had a whole laundry list of ideas.
有的是我的.有的是你的
Maybe it was me, maybe it was you.
你是一F
You're a team.
-可能是我  -什N猜想？
- Maybe was me. - What, what's the idea?
在50年代  有一些高海拔的
There was some high altitude bomb testing
炸y
back in the 50s.
或S是一些射  或S使他放出的高l噪音(嘶嘶)
Maybe it's leftover radiation, maybe our hiss for them.
但@些都逐up弱  可我接收到的呢
But it would diminish over time, and what we were getting?
完全不，]c改
Totally constant, no diminishing.
回到我那清
Back to the laundry list.
虼W  三一W院
1963年春
夏R  尼斯  ]e
Sciama. Dennis, yes.
嗯，我不清楚，是S-H-A-R-M-A@N拼？
Er, I don't know. S-H-A-R-M-A?
他好像是x大利裔
I think he is Italian.
您是尼斯・夏R
Dennis Sciama?
正是
Yes.
我是弗m克・霍金
Frank Hawking.
用W及
理物理部
你好  小夥
Hello, young man.
我之前JR？
Do I know you?
我是史蒂芬・霍金
Stephen Hawking.
我曾申您做我的博
I, I applied for you to supervise my Ph.D.
那r我太忙，所以拒^了。是幔
Too busy, was I?
我想是的
Yes, I think so.
X子  子  有票子
Brains, balls, and cash.
是N意思?
I'm sorry?
物理Wg界在我是血腥的
Physics, in this country is a battle field and a bloody one.
本碛刑熨x就行了，但F是酷的
You need brains which ought to be enough but it isn't,
因槟愕糜绣X去Y助你用大X的地方
because you need cash to fund whatever your brain is working on.
然後你要去e人]拉走的助
And to get cash no one has in this country,
最後要有，是因榭有人和你
you need balls because they'll try and stop you.
你碰到的  x好n}了
You will see. You found the subject?
有什N想法
Any ideas?
]
I don't know yet.
等你想好了  要住
Well, when you do, remember this:
你要槟闼信奉的真理Y到底
You have to fight for what you believe in to the nail,
不然e的混蛋就把你踩在_下
or the buggers will stop you.
物理就是他的一切
Physics means everything to him.
我希望他快  夏R先生
I want him to be happy, Mr. Sciama.
我能做c什N？
What can I do?
我希望你能o他一目
I want you to set him a question that he can... finish.
在他死前能蜉p完成
Something easy enough for him to finish,
的n}
before he dies.
求您了.
Please.
我的W生和我的科研是我的一切
My students and my science are everything to me.
我{良心做事
I try to be true to both,
所以我不能偏袒他  霍金t生
which is why I can't do what you asked me, Dr. Hawking.
很抱歉
I'm sorry.
宇宙W  @T不H的科W
Cosmology. The "get-told" Science,
只有猜想]有C
all speculation no proof...
不H？
"Get -told" Science?
"我怎N淼  未碛⒃
"How we got here, where we're going,
rg是什N"  ξ碚f都是H橹匾的}
what is time?" Ask us all sort of big questions.
史蒂芬
Stephen!
想到n}了  有什N好c子？
Have you got a subject? You brought a big idea back with you?
-]  -有rg  多得是
- No. - Plenty of time, plenty of time.
二十世o物理界最ゴ蟮某删
The greatest achievement to physics in the twentieth century,
_斯福  W本海默  他Ыo我什N
Roosevelt, Oppenheimer, what have they given us?
核武器
The atomic bomb.
我怎N恚未⒃
What's the point in asking
@有什N意思？
how we got here and where we are going,
反正垡蛩固购湍@砘镆呀...
if Einstein and your mob've already got us all ready for...
你樵子怪垡蛩固咕拖轱wC失事
Blaming Einstein for that is like blaming Isaac Newton for
怪以撒・牛DlF了重力
plane crashes because he discovered gravity.
q
Very clever.
真明，可用不到我的生活呀（事上1954年K已有了核站）
Very smart. But those smart isn't real world, is it?
宇宙W家也φ世界不感d趣
Cosmologists is not interested in the real world.
-你看那女孩了  -她怎N了
- Do you see that girl? - What about her?
史蒂芬她凵纤
Stephen is going to make her fall in love with him.
只用垡蛩固沟南φ就行
Using only Einstein's theory of relativity.
讨
George?
要我f@不可能
Tom says it can't be done.
我真的X得@不太合m
I really don't think it is a good idea.
我系的面子岌岌可危啊
The honor and integrity of our entire subject is at stake here.
好吧  好吧
All right. All right.
上吧
Do it.
一杯加K汁的u尾酒  我想是...
One ginger tonic. And I think it's...
抱歉  你知道rg
Excuse me, you got the time, please?
我的rg是七c半  你的rg呢
I make it half pass seven, what time do you make it?
你已知道c了
You already know the time.
只知道我的rg
I know my time.
你_玩笑吧
Are you trying to be funny?
rgK不是普m量
Time is not universal quantity.
我以前以樗是的
We used to think that it was,
我以前以rg就那N存在著
we used to think that it was just there,
於任意地c的任意人，
marching on at the same pace
rg流逝的速度一涌
for everyone everywhere,
就像K行的o限延伸著的F
like a railway track that stretches to infinity.
rg曾被J槭怯a存在的
Time was eternal.
F在我知道它不是
Now we know it isn't.
你得知道探究它的重要性！
You have to know this is incredibly important.
rg不能作⒄瘴铮它不是^Φ
Time is not background thing, it is not absolute,
不同於其他有固定实⒖枷担它是B的
against which everything else is measured. It's dynamic.
B的
Dynamic?
很l繁
Active.
l繁？
Active?
]e  假O你向|做高速直\
Wonderful. If you were to travel east very very quickly...
野以外？h|？
Out of sight? The far east?
比h|h
The far far east.
完全找不到影？
Completely out of sight？
. 完全看不到
Yes, completely out of sight.
而我留在@
And I stay right here,
相於我，你的rg流逝得更慢
your time will slow down relative to mine.
那我就得非常非常慢了
Like I get really really slow?
如果你能走得非常非常快
If you went very very fast.
如果我走得非常非常快
If you went very very fast?
我就得非常非常慢了
I get really really slow!
你的rg相ξ业rg就慢了
Your time would, relative to mine.
呃....完全不懂
Hah...totally out of sight.
rg是很重要的
Time is very important.
我怎NJR你的？
What starts I know you?
什N  我不知道
What? I don't know.
你]事吧
Are you all right?
挺好
Fine.
你要硪槐
Did you want another?
那是l
Who's that?
_堋づ砹_斯  天才啊
Roger Penrose. Brilliant brain.
三年龋他必上教授
He would be a professor within three years.
抱歉  我能再硪槐
Sorry, could I?
是@拥模呃..我.呃..
The thing is, er...just then, er,
我在想W}  ]注意
I was thinking about mathematics and not pay attention,
有r我在想另一S度的W}
sometimes I'm thinking of numbers in a different dimensions
然後]法R上回^神斫釉
I can't come back very quickly to words
@我控制不了
being whether I want it or not,
因槲夷X海中浮F著S多鼍埃
it's because of pictures in my head I...
我r不知道怎N描述
don't know how to make the words come.
明白幔
You see?
根本]
（？@什N口音呀）at all
好的  xx
Yes, please.
H鄣暮
Dear Jane
H鄣暮  我挺好
Dear Jane  I`m fine
差诺墓芟肪曲  太^浪漫  瓦格{很瞧不起他
Poor orchestration, overly romantic. Wagner despised him.
英雄所略同
The feeling was mutual.
什N
What?
勃拉姆斯也瞧不起瓦格{
Brahms despised Wagner.
你不能@颖
Well, you can't compare the two for one thing that...
史蒂芬！
Stephen!
怎N了
Yes.
你好啊
Hello?
你好
Hello.
你]事吧
Are you all right?
我]事
I'm fine.
挺好的
Fine.
我]事
I'm fine.
丹是座Oz(哈姆雷特--莎士比)
Denmark's a prison.
那@世界可是Oz
Then is the world one?
世界是一大囚牢，那e面有那N多O房、囚室、地牢
A goodly one; in which there are many confines,
牢\和地牢  丹是最牡囊蛔
wards and dungeons, Denmark being one o' the worst.
我可不@NJ  ，王子殿下
We think not so, my lord.
那只是你不@NJ
Why, then, 'tis none to you;
]有什N是^Φ暮门c
for there is nothing either good or bad,
但是於人而言就可@N看
but thinking makes it so:
ξ碚f  @就是一座Oz
To me .it is a prison.
那N，是您的野心影你@N看的
Why then, your ambition makes it one;
您的心胸太M隘
'tis too narrow for your mind.
上帝啊  即使我身困於果ぶ中
O God, I could be bounded in a nut shell
仍自以槭o限宇宙之王！（霍金的著作rg史中也引用了@句）
and count myself a king of infinite space！
在我的度e  我不再有趑|
where it not that I have bad dreams.
你在想什N
What are you thinking?
我在..呃..想垡蛩固购拖φ
I was...er...thinking about Einstein and the relativity.
噢
Oh.
-有星星   -嗯
-And stars.   -Oh.
一w超新星可能消失(坍s成橐活w中子星或者黑洞)
It's possible for a perfect star to collapse into nothingness.
如果它是很完美的球w
If it's a perfect sphere than
那它就能坍圮成o限密的物w
it can collapse and become infinitely dense,
密度之大  能蛭引一切物|
so dense that everything is pulled down into nothing.
但必得符合先Ql件
But the conditions have to be right.
什N前提？
What conditions?
如果恒星是完美的球w
Yeah, if it is a perfect sphere,
如果那e很邀  很美（意g不出，只好直g）
if a place has been very moving, if even it's very beautiful.
前提l件必是理想的
The condition has to be ideal,
才有可能然引力阻止任何
and is possible for the pull of the gravity,
物w逃逸
to stop everything escaping,
把一切w於o
everything in nothing.
哦，不！
Oh, no!
我]那N差吧？
Wasn't that bad, was it?
我的包  我落在≡毫
My bag, I left it in the theatre.
我走吧
Shall we?
你能看到星星  看  在那  看到]
Oh, can you see these stars? Look, there, see?
就是它！
Found it!
哈姆雷特什N都]
Hamlet doesn't act.
他逃自己的命\. 如果他做了，真的做了什N...
That is his fate to avoid. If he acted, if he did something...
”揪鸵s水了
Shorten the play.
那保住他的命
It saves his life.
每人都想能逃自己的命\
Everybody wants that.
我在槟阆胝n}
I've been thinking about the subject for you.
法拉第磁致旋光如何
Faraday rotation?
o聊
Boring.
R赫原理呢
Mach's principle?
我看^公式 表述的不蚓_
Formulations I've seen that. Not well defined.
那可是我Y的公式
They are my formulations.
宇宙不嗯蛎  星系互相hx
The universe expands, as galaxies move apart,
有新的星系填上它留下的空位
new galaxies are formed to fill the gaps left behind.
二者的速率大小好
The new replaces the old at just the right rate.
什N都不改
Nothing changes.
不管你身宇宙的哪一角落
Wherever you are in the universes,
仙女座星系 火星是斯卡伯勒
Andromeda, Mars or Scarborough,
看到的情r都是一拥模因槭如此
it always looks the same, because it is the same.
我想做c有意x的事
I want to do something significant.
@宇宙在恒B
The universe, is a steady state universe.
-@才是恒吸引我的  -停
- It's a very attractive steady state for me. - Cut!
-xx大家  -也我安心
-Thank you, gentlemen. - And reassuring.
@怎Nv
Yes?
或S它具吸引力是因樗具有真正的魅力
Maybe it's attractive because it's really reassuring.
情感上碚f，@是很y接受
Emotionally it is far hard to conceive that
宇宙有起c的事，但宇宙K不是如A弧一o起c.Y尾。
the universe has started, the universe hasn't always been around.
根垡蛩固沟睦碚？
Einstein?
他的タ前o古人後o碚
Nobody did what he's worked.
看起硭好像A知到了宇宙有起源
Looks like he's predicting there was a beginning to the universe.
但他一_始就避_了@}
He ran away from the prospect from the beginning.
不  他知道.同r他知道@宇宙有起源的事
No, because he saw the beginning
cT多科W定理相n突
would mean a breakdown of all the laws of science.
科W要怎N解不存在的事？
How can science explain something that isn't there?
@就有了“宇宙大爆炸”的猜想
That's the thing about the idea of a Big Bang.
大爆炸理的^c是e的
The thing about the idea of a Big Bang is that he's wrong.
匪夷所思  而且是e的
Irrational, and wrong.
@是我起的名 大爆炸  我的~
It's my term, Big Bang, I made it up.
知道我槭颤N@N叫
Do you know why I call it that?
因槁上去像卡通赢
Because it sounds like a cartoon.
大爆炸理是卡通物理
The Big Bang theory is cartoon physics.
尼斯也成@  Σ  一起去吃午吧？
Dennis agrees with this, don't you, Dennis? Lunch?
教皇支持大爆炸
The pope is the Big Bang man.
槭颤N
Because?
因榇蟊炸之前 一切都是o
Because before the Big Bang, there was nothing.
]有空g  ]有rg  ]有物|
no space, no time, no matter,
]有科W  ]有世俗  你才有l存在？
no science, no rules, which leaves room for? Guess who?
o所不能的主呀！
Lord God Almighty！
宗教是科W的死  年p人
Religion is the enemy of science, young man.
如果天主教道  那地球是平的
If Catholicism had its way, we all still live in a flatter,
而且是宇宙的中心  _下有地z
at the centre of the universe with the hell down below
天堂就煸谠铝恋淖筮
and the heaven just so much on the left of the moon.
F在是1963年了  上帝那套完了
This is 1963, God is dead.
e去想大爆炸  卡通於你只有面影
Stay away from Big Bangs, cartoons are bad for you.
白色^材料
White dielectric material.
什N意思？
I'm sorry?
大量的他，在B有天的喇叭e
Lots of them. Inside antenna horn.
一定是@樱一定是@原因造成的高l噪音。
Had to be it, had to be the cause of the hiss.
-白色^材料？  -]e
- White dielectric material? - Yes.
子S  喇叭上到都是
Pigeon shit, all over the horn.
知道我做了什N
You know what we did?
-y以置信  -y以置信
- Unbelievable. - Unbelievable.
你质颤N了
What did you do?
我⑺寄出去了
We posted them.
子？
The pigeons?
我把子寄出去了
We posted the pigeons.
我雇主的炔苦]箱
The people we worked for had
有遍讶美k公C
an internal mail and offices are all over American.
我把子送到量h的地方
We posted the pigeons as far away as we can send them.
有用幔
Did it work?
他w回砹
They came home.
@些子很偌
There was the homie pigeons.
他就是不肯走
They weren't ready to leave.
然後你怎Nk
So what did you do?
他...他...
He, he, er...
我人把@些子一射死
We, had the pigeons shot.
不  是U勃人打死了子
No, Bob had the pigeons shot.
你⒘锁子？
You killed the pigeons?
一技gT
A technician.
是一技gT⒌
A technician killed the pigeons.
然後我把那些
And we cleared out all the
白色^材料睦叭e清乾Q
white dielectric material from inside the horn.
我穿著白大褂，跪在那e
On our hands and knees, in our white lab coats,
H手⒛切┌咨材清楚
inside the horn scraping away the white stuff.
然後呢
And?
那些子是o辜的
The pigeons were innocent.
嘶嘶]有消失
The hiss was still there.
子S不是罪魁首
The pigeons' shit was not the hiss.
@诱f得w幔  可以在上@Nf
Is that all right? Can I say that in the television?
我哪ee了  尼斯
What was I doing wrong, Dennis?
尼斯
Dennis?
砹
Yap.
能再o我c幔
Do you think I could get more papers?
尼斯房e有  你知道在哪
Dennis's study. You know where it is.
是史蒂芬
It's Stephen.
你喜g彼此的  等著瞧
I think you'll like each other, you watch.
又是一D高qC物理的午餐了
Another lunch of advanced dialectical physics.
-你好  -你好
- Hello. - Hello.
要番茄幔糠茄薄片
Tomatoes. Could you? Thin slices.
你好  我是_堋づ砹_斯
Hello. Roger Penrose.
是  我知道
Yes, I know.
你JR
Have you two met?
（？）  e客獍
（？）  Help yourselves.
莫札特可以睡一X
Mozart could go to sleep,
醒砟X海e就有一套完整的交
and wake up with whole symphony in his head
]人能蚪忉@
and no idea how they got there.
一整首交  @怎N可能呀？
Whole symphony in his head complete. How can that be?
音作是`光一F的
Music is temporal.
怎N在一瞬g就能作出一整首的交纺
How can you pack a whole symphony into just one moment?
或S作音返乃季S方式
Or maybe it's because music is a way of thinking
是只可意不可言鞯
that goes way beyond language.
或S@才是天才
May be that's what genius is.
思考只需要瞬g
Thinking without time.
ll大路通物理
All the roads lead to physics.
我J樗季S
I think thought,
W思S  是能蛲耆不用言Z表_的
mathematical thought can exist completely without words.
我不J樗季S是Z言化的
I don't think thinking is verbal, in fact,
我X得Z言反而妨K了思S
I think words come in the way.
Z言反而是思S的bO
I think you can do without words.
一直以恚人rg十分感d趣
Poets have always been obsessed with time.
企D嚎s它  操控它  阻止它前M
Shrinking it, controlling it, stopping it.
艾略特就^（艾略特《四月是最忍的一月》）
Thomas Sterns Eliot
"^去和F在或S都⒊尸F在未
"Time present and time past are both perhaps present
而未碇杏痔N含了^去
in time future, and time future contained in time past."
伯特・布克
Rupert Brooke
"教堂的停在x三c十分的地方"
"Stands the Church clock at ten to three."
牙卓  "一沙一世界
Blake. "To see a world in a grain of sand,
一花一天堂
and a heaven in a wild flower,
君掌盛o  刹那含永劫[宗白Ag]"
hold infinity in the palm of your hand, and eternity in an hour."
有首五行打油
And limerick.
l的
Who?
有小姑娘  名叫亮WW（o}，作者A. H. Buller，後肀桓木成歌，霍金也引用^）
There was a young lady named Bright,
_底抹了油  速度^光
whose speed was much faster than light.
一日出T去  走上相β
she set out one day, in a relative way,
待到w家  已是前一晚
and returned on the previous night.
是不定的
It's unstable.
什N
Sorry?
^mf
Go on.
是不定的
It's unstable!
你造新物|就需要一反能量
You need the negative energy field
那泳得很不定
in order to create the new matter which makes it unstable.
你f霍伊的恒BWf？
Hoyle's steady state?
@是有}的吧
It's a problem, isn't it?
是不是
Isn't it?
你很喜g霍金  Σ
You like Hawking very much, don't you?
她剩下多久的rg？
Will he have the time?
什N
What?
他是否碛凶虻rg他去追求他的粝耄
Does he have enough time left to get what he's after?
希望如此
I hope so.
用W及
理物理部
一具有rgΨQ性的新重力理
A time symmetric new theory of gravity.
非常精彩  @是霍伊的最佳理
It's brilliant. Hoyle's best.
他原硎悄愕牟幔
Did you start as his Ph.D. student?
你想要我的碗啊
Are you after my job?
-是不是  -那你呢
- Did you? - Are you?
不是
No?
他是ゴ蟮目W家
Yes, he is a great scientist.
你的n}是演算@w星炔亢ず量
You work on the deduction of the helium inside the stars.
@是...怎Nf呢...
It's...eh,what's the word...
漂亮  @也是
Beautiful, and so is this.
我做校
I do the checking.
他交由委T硇Φ
It should be referred by the committee but
但霍伊]那工夫
Hoyle doesn't have the time.
我能看看
Can I see it?
我得走了
I have to go.
再我看一
Just give me a few moment.
我F在急的要走
I have to go now.
那就留在我@
Leave it with me.
好吧  但e...
OK, but don't...
怎N？我能吃了它
What? Eat it?
看完放我桌上
Just leave it on my desk.
起的真早
Up early
你]事吧
Are you all right?
挺好
Fine.
你看上去像是昨晚玩得很high
You look like you have a wild night.
差不多吧
Something like that.
呃，今天下午去皇家科W院作蟾妫
So the Royal Society this afternoon?
你今天就要l表文
You are giving the paper today?
Yes.
您得史蒂芬・霍金吧
You, remember Stephen Hawking?
敦  皇家W院
1964年夏
我x予@理一新的公式
The new theory we have formulated
c我熟知的理有所不同
differs in its global implications from the usual theory,
在我所熟知的理中
in that, whereas, in the usual theory,
龇匠瘫壤常档呢
the negative sign of the the constant proportionality
是任意添加或去掉的
which appears in the field equations is chosen arbitrarily.
在新的定xe  不存在@拥牟淮_定
In the new theory, there's no such ambiguity.
符必樨值，而且值的大小必和G(重力加速度)相等
The sign must be minus and further, that magnitude of G,
是由物|的平均密度而Q定的
follows on from a determination of the mean density of matter.
因此，一宇宙W家就能知道
Thereby enabling the cosmologist to know
如果他落已  摔得多重
how hard he'll hit the ground if he falls off a cliff.
有什N}
Any questions?
你有什N要f  年p人
Did you want to say something, young man?
你的算出e了
Your calculation is wrong.
高l散
The advanced field diverges.
高霾l散
The advanced field does not diverge.
不，我想他是的。  你全e了
No, I'm afraid it does. It's all wrong.
你能ff你是怎N知道的  年p人
Would you like to tell us how you know this, young man?
我算出砹
I worked it out.
你是在演v^程中算出淼
You worked it out dunning the lecture?
不  我之前就稍微看了下你的文
No, I had a previously shown only a glimpse of the paper.
l你@N做的
Who put you up to that?
什N
What?
才的事是l指使你做的
That stance in there. Who put you up to it?
有人指使你斫o我vy
Somebody's put you up to sabotaging me.
e了就是e了，我不是已解了幔
It's just wrong, that's all, I did say it, didn't I?
@理是e的
The physics is wrong!
你致锇颜文o他看
Why did you show him the paper?
我不想我的文o任何混蛋看（bugger有`者的意思）
I hate them being shown to any bugger.
科W不是唱大
Science isn't a theatre.
有人指出e`的
It needed to be said.
就一定要用才那N方式？！
In that way?
我做你博Ф嗑昧
How long has it been since you started with me?
你不喜g我攻
You don't like the idea of me attacking
-恒B理  -你]回答我的}
- steady state theory. - You didn't answer my question.
因槟阕约壕椭С趾惴B理
Because you are a steady state man yourself.
好吧  我替你回答  十二月了
OK, I'll answer it for you. Twelve months.
所以我攻艉惴B理的想法...
So the idea of me attacking steady state...
我父H是_棉S的
My father ran a cotton mill.
我21q那年  我告V他
When I was 21, I told him
我要做物理W家  他O度反Α
I wanted be a physicist, he hated the idea.
他他希望他的事I能蛟谖业氖种鞒邢氯ァ
He wanted me to take over the business from him.
所以他f除非我用W金自理
So he told me that I couldn't be a physicist
否t就e想物理W家
unless I got a fellowship to pay for it.
他以槲易霾坏
He thought I wouldn't get it.
他以槲抑皇侨分岫取Ｎ蚁窆芬勇淦堑仄疵
He thought I would buck. I worked like a dog...
@跟我攻艉惴BWf有什NPS
What is this to do with me attacking steady state?
我理解人生的道路上受阻的感X
I know what is it like to have obstacles in your path,
我知道吃]T羹的感受
I know what is it like to be told you can't do something,
@就是我去老的原因
that's why I became a teacher.
我永h不因橐庖不合
I would never ever stop a student of mine from pursuing something
而去阻K我的W生去追逐他的粝
because I didn't agree with their opinion.
永h不
Never.
我知道你除了明地攻e人能做更多
I know you can do more than make brilliant attacks on others.
去做c凫赌愕|西
Do something, all of your own.
原的
Be original.
心！
Look out!
醉了幔
Drunk?
或S是~s
Maybe it's New York.
或S是~sl出的高l噪音
Maybe the hiss is New York with it.
~s ？ 怎N是那？
New York? How?
我在想.世界上哪座城市能蜥放出
We figure that if any city in the world
三彷射的噪音
could give you three degrees of hot radio noise
那必是~so疑（Big Apple是~s的eQ）
it must be the Big Apple.
我自己家就找得出
My family alone could probably make the much of hiss.
我在猜有什N可能性
We were struggling the thing what else it could be.
你的猜想是？
You're guessing?
有@N多的|西干_
How could we claim we've been making
我怎N能Q我已做了
very sensitive radio astronomy measurements
精密的天文y量呢
with that all man-made stuff around?
我把天指向~s市
We pointed the antenna the New York City.
所有的能量都分言诒边的地平
All that energy spread out across the northern horizon,
地Fl出的火花  l出的蜂Q
arking from sub-rails, hummers from power lines,
甘迪C龅睦走_放大器
the radar amplifier at Kennedy airport
l出浊瓦的s
spilling out radio noises by the kilowatts.
然後我想。可能，只是可能，@座城
And I'm thinking, just maybe, just maybe, this town,
可能就是3高l噪音的源^
this town of all towns might crank up three degrees of hiss!
你f你碜缘
You've said that you were from Germany.
你什Nr候x_德的
When did you leave Germany?
或S我先停拍
Maybe we should stop filming.
我六qrS家人淼矫
We came to American when I was six years old.
我住在服b^的二室公寓e（生a服b的S^周）
We lived in a 2-room apartment in the Garment District.
我  我弟弟  我父母和N房的蟑螂一起居
Me and my brother and my parents and cockroaches in the kitchen.
我那r很F  @就是槭颤N我做了物理W家
We were poor. That's why I became a physicist,
不是榱甏箦X  不是榱酥Z
not to get rich, not to win the Nobel,
只是不想再做F人
to stop being poor.
嘶嘶不是碜约~s
New York, wasn't it.
我把20英尺的天指向~s
We pointed 20 feet horn at the city.
他回了一合理的量，但是
It gave us a reasonable amount but-
不蛸|的嘶嘶
Not enough hiss.
程度不
Not enough.
要A得Z  需要lF什N
To win the Nobel Prize you have to find something.
Z提名不出自猜想或理
Am I right? It's not about thinking or theory.
是o予探索clF的
It's about discovery.
但是找到的不一定就是你想要的
But do you have to be looking for the thing that you find?
科W研究有r成持久
Science can be slow work.
缀]l在洗澡的r候`光一F（阿基米德c流wo力W第一定理）
It's hardly ever about eureka moments in the bath.
你得精益求精  皂g不拔  全心全意
You need precision, tenacity, dedication.
德人的生淼拈L
German talents.
有人找你  霍金先生
Your visitor, Mr. Hawking.
他目不D睛地盯著我
He wouldn't let me out of sight, not once.
好像我能打劫似的
Scared me out of my mug, I think.
矩矩@N多┪目d
Oh, rules, rules, rules!
彭_斯在敦有演v  你聿恚
Penrose's lecture in London. Otherwise engaged?
史蒂芬  你]事吧
Stephen? Are you all right?
挺好的  挺好的
Fine, fine.
噢.你的口^U
Oh, your two favourite words.
我F在找你合m幔
Is it all right for me to have come?
挺好的
Fine.
不  不你呢
No, it's not your turn.
你在致
What are you doing?
t是.我打歪了要再打一次
It's in the rules, I've cricketed it and so I go again.
你能一直@N打下去
Can you keep doing that?
然能了
Of course I can.
你要把你的球
So what you are supposed to do get your pair of balls
打得量h  然後...
as far away from it as possible and then.....
怎N了  你笑什N
What? What is it? What you're doing, croaking?
等等  彭_斯在敦的演v
Hold on. A Penrose lecture in London.
]PS  快去吧  去工作啊
It's all right. Go, now! Work!
你的右臂上的二^肌都很l_
You all have big biceps, on the right arms.
因槟用大半生
Because you spent half of your lives
走^成e的黑板  u造了成的粉P灰
scoring tons of chalk dust, across miles of blackboard.
而我...
I...
不那N做
Don't do that.
我有一神奇的美妙的|西要告V你
I have something magic and wonderful to tell you about.
它很快  很有活力
It's fast, it's vigorous,
而且用不上l_的二^肌  它叫拓
and you don't need big muscles. It's called topology.
研究D形  而不是方程
Pictures, not equations.
光是最快的
And nothing moves faster than light.
秒速186000英里  光速是最快的
Under 186,000 miles per second, light is the fastest,
它的速度它p地克服了引力（第三宇宙速度1.67km/s）
easily fast enough to overcome the gravity pull of,
而x了太
say, the sun,
和地球  跑了出去
or the Earth, and escaped.
它的速度快到
The speed is high enough
能[拉住它的引力
to get away from the gravity pulling it back.
如果太...
What if the sun...
密度再大一c呢
were more concentrated?
如果太坍s了呢
What if the sun were collapsed?
他的密度得很大，亩引力很大（F＝GmM/r^2）
The density becomes huge, the gravity pull enormous.
]什N能蛱右
And now nothing could stop
⒁磺卸技{入其中，甚至光
gravity pulling everything in - even light.
奇c就形成了
A singularity forms.
奇c是什N呢
What is singularity?
奇c是一地方  所有物|  光  空g
A singularity is a place where matter, light, space...
rg   一切
Time.  Everything.
物理W奇c，全Q“奇c”.物理W上一存在又不存在的c。
都被扭曲，然後消失
Fold in on themselves, and dissappear.
它深邃，以至氐椎奶o~
It's profound, and total nothingness.
一切w
Everything in nothing.
迄今，所有些繁}的公式
And up until now, all of you people
有二^肌l_的人 是f
with your big biceps and your big equations, have always said,
"我的公式
"Oh, my big equation
以奇cY束了  我肯定是e了"
is ending in a singularity, I must be wrong."
垡蛩固咕褪潜贿@倒了
That's what frightened Einstein.
奇c不可能存在
Singularities can't exist
因榭W的定律不S它存在
because the laws of science don't allow for them.
e了  奇c存在
Wrong. Singularities do exist.
只能是完美的球w  理想之星
For perfect sphere, for ideal light stars.
不  真存在的恒星
No, for real stars.
真正的恒星也@  奇c是存在的
Real stars do it, too. Singularities are out there.
在有些地方  科W和定律不再m用
There are places where science and rules break down
]有物|  ]用空g  什N都]有
where there is no matter, no space, nothing,
所有|西  包括rg  都不存在了
where everything, including time, does not exist.
而一w恒星坍s的r候  奇c的a生o可避免
And when a star collapses, singularity is inevitable.
拓W不去管那些不愉快的部分
Topology doesn't bother with
以及一些糟糕的天w\
the messy stuff about particals and how they move,
而是研究事物的M
it's about how things connect.
往大想
Big thinking.
大地往大的方面想
Big bold thinking.
@幽憔湍芟氲揭恍┒理的禁^
It takes you to places where the rules say you can't go.
我不能放他呀
And it's fast. You say that it is fast.
我δ阋恢倍际f
I've tried to be truthful with you.
所以我F在也是言相告
I'm not going to stop now.
我o能榱α
There's nothing more we can do.
@病是]法治的
There's no treatment to it.
Σ黄
I'm sorry.
他不管他了
They've washed their hands off him.
我得猿窒氯グ
We got to carry on for him.
猿  猿
Carry on, carry on.
我要做的不只是猿帜屈N
We have to do a lot more than carry on.
S生素B  u胺素  要c固醇
Vitamin B? Hydroxocobalamin? And steroids?
我]放你  他e了
I haven't washed my hands off you, they're wrong.
你到了  他e了
You understand that they're wrong? The lot of them!
你牟徽他的病情
You don't ever talk about his illness.
他自己牟徽f
He doesn't speak about it.
我就尊重他的意  很
We respect that, it's simple really.
那你怎N看我呢
What do you think of me?
我是f  你X得我怎Nk
I mean, what do you think that I should do?
Σ黄  @不公平  e回答  讨
Sorry, that's not fair, don't answer, George.
你大概J槲以自己走人
You probably think I should take myself off
回}W本斯去嫁健全的老公
back to St. Albans and look for a nice husband.
我X得你不他的病情很好
I think it's terrific you don't talk about his illness.
{色的艄
Blue lights are picking up
洗衣粉中的光粉更加醒目
the fluorescence you get in washing powder.
那就是槭颤N他的r衫@得更亮
That's why their shirts are luminated.
好奇怪
Very strange.
Y服是新的
Dresses are new.
]有洗^  所以]有光
They haven't been washed so they are not fluorescent.
你看  ゴ蟮目W家
Here you see? Great scientist.
我能告V你
I can tell you all about how
洗衣粉是怎N被{光"染色"的
washing powders react dye in the blue lights.
有史以碜ゴ蟮}
One of the great questions of all time
什N在{光的照耀下@得更醒目
whether tie dazzle in the blue lights.
你想跳舞
Do you want to dance?
我不知道你怎N做
I don't know what you should do.
我知道他想要什N
I know what he wants.
-有房  有花@  有孩子...  -一起生活
- House, garden, children with... - A life together.
@是不可能的
Impossible.
我一直在想伽利略
I've been thinking about Galileo
P於你f他牧舜蠹
and what you said about him frightening people.
想想那是N什N感X
Imagine what it must have felt like
人家告V你f太不是著地球D
to be told that the sun didn't go round the Earth.
多恐怖啊  或者f地球不是平的
Horrible, or the earth isn't flat.
是平的啊
It is, isn't it?
是平的    e跟我f不是
Flat, Jane. Don't tell me it isn't flat.
那可不行
Oh, no, oh, no,
你F在要是看著我f
You looked me in the eye now and told me
地球不是平的  我不知道要怎Nk好
that it isn't flat and I don't know what I will do,
我  我心欲^  y^地死掉
I'll be... I'll be inconsolable, totally death of it.
史蒂芬
Stephen!
你r知道@是什N
Did you have any idea what it might be?
你心e有
Did you think you knew?
是俨y
Or was it just guessing?
你是想f@
Is that what you're trying to say?
ZCo最佳猜想  @就是你的
A Nobel Prize for guesswork? Is that story you're after?
我告V你  在拍z
Let me tell you something, are we still fiming?
好  很好
Good, good.
1939年  我父母送我上了一v火
In 1939, my mother and father put me on a train
火d著一q太小孩向英
filled with the Jewish childern headed to England.
避y和＞
Kindertransport.
二鸨l前九月  英接{了碜约{粹德
W匈帝  波m等的q太和近f人
他大都逃^了的劫y
你]事吧
Are you OK?
r{粹只放走了一些孩子
The Nazis were, letting some children go,
大人不行  只S孩子走
not the adults, just some children.
在月_上  我看著我
At the station, my mother looked into my face,
ξ艺f要照好我弟弟
and said for me to looked out for my little brother,
一直盯著我的行李箱
not to let our suitcase out of my sight and
有不能G了名  阿Z・彭R在此
don't lose your name tag, Arno Penzias is here.
名弄G了
You lose your name tag,
你就]名字了  你就什N都]有了
you lose your name and you lose everything.
然後她就走了
And she went.
你r多大
How old were you?
我六q
I was six.
你後碇胤炅
Did you see her again?
我六q  我弟弟五q
I was six, my little brother was five.
她]哭
She didn't cry.
她@一切看起硭坪踉僬常不^
She made like it was a normal thing,
而正常的事就不能哭
and not crying was part of that.
你能想像不哭出碛卸嚯y
Can you image how hard it must have been not to cry?
把你的鹤铀蜕夏右惠v火而不哭出
To put your boys on a train like that and not to cry.
我那以後就一直行李箱
I've hated suitcases ever since.
他喜g打_行李箱
He likes to unpack.
我父母逃出了德
My mother and my father got out.
六月後我一起去了美
Six month later we sailed for American together.
英救了我一命
England saved my life.
美o了我新的生命
America gave me a brand-new one.
但我]  ]想到有@一天
But I never, I never dreamed of this happening.
我lF了@  我找到了它  lF了它
We discovered this. We found this, we discovered this.
@是什N
What it is?
@...
This clock...
我拿到r好好的  等我拿回
It's fine when I got it, when I went to America,
就_始倒著走
it started to run backwards.
我的W生rg的本|
Stops my students getting too complacent
不那N洋洋自得
about that nature of time.
-我不知道我碜...  -  音
- I don't know why I came here... - Listen to this, music.
巴赫]完
Bach didn't finish it.
他死了  ]能完成
He died before he finished it.
但它如此完美
But it's so perfect.
它]有完成就如此完美
Everything is done before it's so perfect... it doesn't end.
Y束r你能到  你
You can here it after it stops. Listen.
得到幔
Can you hear?
我蛞
I'll see you in Cambridge.
我以槭俏走了呢
I thought that was us.
我也是
So did I.
但不是
But it wasn't.
是他走了
No, it's them.
F在又往後退了  我要待一段rg了
Backwards now, we are having a time of it.
就怪@月_  一月_
It is the platform. Platform one.
@月_牟恢苯油前走
It's never straight forward here,
你不知道接下l生什N
you don't know what's going to happen next.
我有r候跟我丈夫f  他s不M去
Sometimes I told my husband about it but he doesn't listen.
他只f"一月_  是虻脑屡_嘛
He just says: "It's Platform one, it's the Cambridge platform,
然l生奇怪的事了
of course strange things are going to happen,
是虻脑屡_嘛"
it's the platform for Cambridge."
]人知道@是l的月_  可...
Nobody else knows if it's their platform, Cambridge...
向後  向後
Backwards, Backwards.
Yes.
反^淼  ]e  rg的走向
It reversed. Oh, of course it reversed, the direction of time.
你在用虻rg
Yes. Are you in Cambridge time?
我非常勰  直到永h
Yes, and I love you deeply and forever!
_  _
Roger! Roger!
_堋づ砹_斯  _堋づ砹_斯  站住
Roger Penrose! Roger Penrose! Stop!
你]事吧
Are you right?
什N
What?
如果垡蛩固故Φ哪
What if Einstein was right.
什Nα
About what?
UP
Pencil! And some paper!
粉P
Chalk?
rg和空g  哪出F的更早？
Time space diagram, what comes first?
空g  rg
Space? Time?
你把序反^硐
You have to think about reversing the direction of time.
用另一N序
Time coming in the other way.
什N  槭颤N
What, what for?
想啊  e停下  想
Go on, don't stop, go on!
F在  此r此刻
Um... now, the present dust?
我在此往回看rg
Here we are, looking back through time,
光  和宇宙中的密集物|
light, dense matter in space.
影著空g的rg
Wobbling space time?
⒐饩...
Causing the matter rays,
把光向彼此
bending the matter rays towards each other.
看  ^去融R到一起
Look! The past is patching.
你什N意思
What are you saying?
如果整宇宙
What if the whole of the universe was
都困在一既]有界也]有力的^域e
trapped in a region with no boundary, strenghth, is zero.
奇c  o
The singularity? Nothingness?
你的理  能用斫忉坍圮
Your theory. Works for collapsing.
垡蛩固  他C明了奇c一定存在
Einstein, he proves that singularity must have existed,
如果@也m用呢
what if it works for this, it could only work,
_  如果能m用意味著什N
Roger, what would it mean if it did?
坍圮反^
A collapse and reverse.
是爆炸
An explosion.
大爆炸
Bang!
抱歉  你f什N
Sorry, what?
你f什N
What are you saying?
下
Write it down.
你下戆
Why don't you write it down?
抱歉  夥
Sorry, mate.
三一W院
Trinity Hall.
@影  他是怎N了
Oh, right. What's the matter with him?
你f^跎主教
Have you heard of Bishop Usher?
十七世o
Seventeenth century.
他算出宇宙起c的日期
He calculated the date of the start of the universe.
怎N算的
How?
他把《fs》e所有人的年g加在了一起
By adding up all the ages of people in the Old Testament.
他的宇宙有多大
And how old is his universe?
大s始於西元前4004年
It started at some point in the night
10月22日的一晚上
of the 22nd of October, 4004BC.
-真老啊  -真老
- So old. - So old.
我有件事想你
Something I want to ask you.
我在月_遇你r正淙ツ
Where was I going when I saw you at the station?
不是
No.
史蒂芬  你]事吧
Stephen? Are you all right?
挺好
Fine.
事上...我在想...
The thing is... I was wondering...
你不意嫁o我
Whether you consider marrying me?
你可能需要些rg
You probably want time to think about it.
我勰
I love you.
@的意思是你要拒^我
Does that mean you're about to say no?
要crg，我要再考]一下
Time. Time to think.
史蒂芬
Stephen.
F在]空  讨
Not now, George.
@是我原的文  史蒂芬・霍金
This dissertation is my original work,S.W.Hamking
我在思考P於r光倒流的}
I'm thinking about time going in the oppsite direction.
什N
What?
奇c
Singularities.
坍s  是f物化樘o
A collapse, everything into nothing, yes?
那N反^  它就成了爆炸
So reverse the time so the collapse is an explosion.
o槿f物
Nothing into everything!
你是f恒星
You're talking about stars?
不  不  我不是在f恒星
No! No, I'm not talking about stars!
我是f宇宙的起源
I'm talking about the beginning of the universe.
_堋づ砹_斯  我找他真是太明智了
That Roger Penrose, clever of me to find him.
我就f你能偷剿
I've told you that you could help him.
我想他是自己做到的
He helped himself, I think.
@是你的另一c
That's your other talent.
-什N  -你^分的t
- What? - Your preposterous modesty.
你在@喊  你跑哪喝チ
There you are. Where have you been?
尼斯・夏R要你  他表情很烂C
Dennis Sciama wants to see you. He seemed very serious!
前三章  Ko新意
The first three chapters, nothing special.
第四章
The forth...
莫札特（神碇P）
Mozart.
哦  你好啊
Oh, hello.
女人是不被允S...
Jane, women are not allowed...
不能M去  `反t
No, not allowed, against the rules.
我...我是走吧
Ah, I'll go.
再
Good-bye.
我要去找罩鞴芤匙
I, er, I have to go and see the bursar for the keys.
我A得W金了
They've given me a fellowship.
一起
Are you coming?
匙分配的t一同仁
And the same rule for everyone are keys.
分房不o任何人特e待遇
No special treatment when it comes to housing.
我跟他不一
I am not like all the rest.
l都@Nf
That's what they all say.
你我f  你好了
Please listen to me, and you listen very carefully.
@人不能上翘
This man cannot walk upstairs.
@是他疾病所致  而且他的情r更加糟糕
His illness will not allow it, his illness will get worse.
他需要分到比^好走的房g
He needs housing with easy access,
不管你去不去，你o他找一比^好走的房g的
and you are going to find it for him because if you don't,
不然所有笊.@所W校的罩鞴芏被告知@所W校
all the newspapers will hear about how the bursar of this college
是怎NΥ一非常勇敢  天xA
treats a man of huge courage, brilliant mind
K能γ\的不公不屑一的人
and capacity to imagine fates like a piece of nothing,
你懂了
You understand me?
而且他⒊槲艺煞
And he is going to be my husband.
他做的是垡蛩固沟墓ぷ
What he's done is to make Einstein work.
他垡蛩固...
He has made Einstein...
有~物理W家都喜g
There's a word that physicists like to use
但是很罕--- 美
very occacionally - beautiful.
他垡蛩固沟睦碚很美
He has made Einstein beautiful.
是的  但是他到底做了什N
Yes, but what, what has he done?
你的鹤哟蜷_了一扇
Your son has opened up something
我以  我都以槭顷P]著的T
which I thought, we all thought, was closed.
垡蛩固顾坪跏穷A言到了它  但他放了
Einstein appeared to be predicting it and then, he turned away.
那可能是宇宙的_端
That could be the beginning.
宇宙  可能K不是一直都存在的
The universe, may not always has been here.
即使你是Φ  但是也有n突
If you're right, which you are not,
按你@Nv，大爆炸留下一些射
there should be left some radiation
而且也有人曾接收到了
from the Big Bang and somebody should have heard it.
但是]人收到  是不是
But they haven't, have they?
你f@是槭颤N
I wonder why that could be?
不是因]有大爆炸呢
Could it be because it isn't there?
C在哪e  霍金  C呢
Where's the fossil, Hawking? Where's the fossil?
我得走了
We have to go on.
@一切息息相P  你明白
It connects. Do you understand?
它穿^了黑洞  穿^了童年
It goes right through dark hole, right through childhood,
穿^了蟑螂和行李箱  穿^了美
right through cockroaches and suitcases and right through America
穿^了我成真的美
and the Ameriacan dream which I have lived.
你懂
You understand me?
@些高l噪音
This noise.
@美的嘶嘶
This goddamn beautiful hiss.
他是相P的
It connects.
@是rg起源的音
It's the sound of the beginning of the time.
是大爆炸留下淼挠
The left over heat from the Big Bang.
我o法降下淼3射
The three degrees that hasn't cooled yet.
o所不在  h@著我
It's everywhere. It's all around us.
有一百五十|的v史（根2010年所得到的最佳的^yY果，@些初始B大s存在l生於133|年至139|年前）
It's fifteen billion  years old.
我找到了它
And we found it.
@就是我的lF
That's our discovery.
我得去I了  阿Z
We have to go to get the Prize, Arno.
那N在大爆炸以前是怎拥模
What was that before the Big Bang?
我不知道是什N
We don't know what it was,
不是rg  不是空g  不是物|
it wasn't time, space or matter.
那是上帝的I域
There's room for God.
理上碚f
Yes, in theory.
那F在做什N
So what now?
我要吃蔓越莓
I'm going to eat cranberry
和一大堆松露巧克力
and a huge number of chocolate truffles.
要M我所能o你形容你瓦格{的作品是多N美妙
And find very hard to get you to see how wonderful Wagner is,
而勃拉姆斯是]那N好
and how Brahms is not so wonderful.
我是^深思熟]的！
I meant with work!
我研究的f物的理都是宏^的
The theories of everything I have been looking at are big.
F在我想研究微^的
And now I want to look at the very small,
看我能不能Y合引力和量子力W
and see how I may unify gravity and quantum mechanics.
理上碚f@要多久
How long might in theory everything take?
不超^二十年
Twenty years no more than that.
@N快啊
That fast.
@N快呢
我相信有@可能性
I believe in the possible.
我的生命如此短海我如此渺小
I believe small though we are, insignificant though we maybe,
但我s有能力理解宇宙
we can reach full understanding of the universe.
仰望著碧落星空才知道自己是多N的渺小
You're right when you said you felt small
你f的]e
looking out the dome down there.
我是很渺小
We're very very small.
但我s能蚨聪つ切┐砘锏谋举|
But we are profoundly capable of very very big things.
你去哪
Where are you going?
去做做的事
Things to do.
你得到幔
Can you hear me?
1978年12月10日  阿Z・彭R斯
和_伯特・威d  因他在1965年lF的
大爆炸的N  而s@Z
弗雷德・霍伊爵士一生T果累累  逝於2001年
他一直]接受宇宙有起c的f法
1994年  _堋づ砹_斯因科W做出艹鲐I
而被授以爵位  他的μ圮恒星的奇c理
被宇宙中lF的黑洞C
史蒂芬和・霍金Y婚25年  育有3孩子
史蒂芬被_\患有\由窠元病已有四十年
他F任虼WW系的R卡斯教授
以撒・牛D曾任此位
翻g中用到的人名翻g自google
部分Y料碜wikipedia，百科
本人力求意g，但是有部分超出了本人理解，只好直g。
有2句未能出原句。敬解
用的w是晨L槿巳擞耙u作的time machine
感xSK臀曳部分翻g。本人第一次做字幕，不足之解.
Fremont